pursuant.
Of the municipal charter for the
city and county of san
francisco.
JANUARY 825 meeting of the san
francisco board of supervisors
is now come to order.
>> gien with the roll call for
attendance.
Pursuant to the rules the roll
call begins at the top of the
alphabet.
Say, present when I call you.
>> supervisor connie chan.
>> present.
>> supervisor chen.
>> present
>> supervisor dorsey.
>> present.
>> supervisor engardio.
>> supervisor jackie fielder.
>> present.
>> supervisor mahmood.
>> supervisor mandelman.
>> present.
>> supervisor melgar.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> present.
>> supervisor sheryl.
>> went and supervisor walton
>> present j. We have a kwoer
and up all members are present.
.
With the new elected returning
members and continuing members
and the department heads of the
california delegation guests
join me in the pledge of
allegiance.
[Pledge of allegiance] 94
communication of credentials,
the office of clerk of the board
is in reach certificates of
election for the new and
reelected members of the board
who received votes at the
election on NOVEMBER 5, 2024.
Staff will come and hand out
your certificates now.
And liberally, we received the
controller's official
certification the surety bond
requirements have been met for
the new reelectd and appointed
member of the board of
supervisors and in district
order.
D1, connie chan
>> d2, sherrill
>> d3.
Sauter.
>> 5, mahmood.
>> d7.
Melgar and d 11 chen.
Now to the oath of office the
meeting start at 2 P.M. To allow
board members to attends the
mayor's inauguration.
Note that pursuant to the
charter all member who is stood
for election and our appointed
member have been sworn in and
their oaths processed prior to
12 noon today by our fantastic
clerk diane.
Thank you.
We now have beginning at 12
o'clock a full compliment of the
board of supervisors
appropriateed address the city's
challenges.
It is our custodyum at this
meeting that we invite the throw
coequal branchs of government to
highlight the system of
government.
Established in the U.S.
Constitution.
It is our hope to exhibit to the
public deintiet divide power
between branches the force work
together as a team to face the
challenges that visit san
francisco. Board will elect its
own to lead this body as the
board PRESIDENT After the mayor
will address the chamber.
Now we are fortunate to are
judiciary represent today is my
privilege to introduce to you
presiding judge of the superior
court of california, the county
of san francisco the honorable
judge east to provide the
ceremonyial oath to be witnessed
by friends and family.
Welcome, judge east.
[Applause]
>> I would like to ask, please,
the new elected reelected and
the appointed members to in
forward and if you will stand
here before me, please.
>> and you will say your name
and I will point to each you you
will say your name individually.
We'll start here.
And go across.
All right.
If you will raise your right
hand.
I, connie chan.
[Inaudible] Do swear, that I
will support and defend the
constitution of the united
states.
And the constitution of the
state of california.
Against all enemies foreign and
domestic.
Thattil bear true faith and
allegiance to the constitution
of the united states and the
constitution of the state of
california.
That I take this obligation
freely, without any mental
reservation.
For purpose of evasion.
And that I will well and
faithfully discharge, the duties
upon which I'm about to enter.
>> and do you recall such time,
as I hold the office, of
commissioner of the san
francisco county transportation
authority.
And member of the san francisco
board of supervisors.
Of the city and county of san
francisco.
Congratulations.
[Applause]
>> thank you.
Presiding judge east.
Now to nominations.
At the meeting on the eighth day
of JANUARY the board of
supervisors shall by a vote
elect PRESIDENT For two year
term.
Before I read the principles for
nominations will members clear
their name.
Once I declier open you MAY
place your name on the roster.
After nominations we'll take
public comment and then a
discussion can occur between the
members.
Are there questions from the
members?
Very good.
>> there are several
principles.
The first is that members MAY
nominate one person.
Either themselves or another
member.
Nominees state on the record if
they accept the nomination.
Nominees stay in the chamber you
don't have to leave you can vote
on your own nomination.
Nominees with draw their own
nomination without a second at
any time.
At completion of nominations
they are closed.
The board MAY adopt a motion to
reopen nominations with the
majority vote.
When notchinations are reopened,
those members who have yet to
nominate MAY do so.
Or a member MAY with draw
previous nomination and nominate
a different member.
Any questions?
All right.
Seeing no questions.
The nominations are declared
open.
Supervisor dorse.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk
temperature is my honor to place
the name of rafael mandelman to
nomination for pedestrian san
francisco board of supervisors.
Most of us who know supervisor
mandelman from his tenure in
this chamber know him as the
longest standing active member
by 6 months.
We know him a long time chair
who presides over this body when
he sit as the transportation
authority.
We know him as a passionate,
occasionally ponderous and only
sometimes weepy champion for
priorities that are close to his
heart and very close to mine to
which prioritize solutions to
our city's substance and
homelessness crisis.
Make goods to housing and reform
requirements to unlook housing
production.
Fight for public transportation
in a time so many of the
agencies san francisco's economy
depends on our facing financial
challenges.
That includes his successful
championship for prop l sales
tooks deliver billion in ref now
for transit in years to come.
Beyond the rafael mandelman most
of you know from this chamber.
I want to share a perspective
the receiveiel I have known for
20 years.
he has been a champ for the
lbgtq+ community from the fight
in 2004 and transinclusive
nondiscrimination act to today's
fight to end transgender
homelessness and aids services
that are a national model.
More than the policy priorities,
which there are too many to
list.
Combha in my view recommended
him to the prosecutesy of the
board is a temp upper ment and
good heart someone who worked
well across lines throughout his
entire public life.
He unique low can bring people
together for a common purpose in
a time that is more needed than
ever before.
I saw him do this as PRESIDENT
Of harvey milk democratic club
in 2008 and when we were
colleagues in 2012ism saw him do
it on the college board if my
perspective the city attorney's
office we fenldz off a push by
creditors that almost shut down
city college of san francisco.
We embark on a new chapter of
san francisco history today,
rafael mandelman is the right
choice to lead this board of
supervisors and I hope you join
mow in supporting him.
>> thank you, supervisor
dorsey nominated supervisor
mandelman for board PRESIDENT.
Supervisor chan.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues I want to welcome our
new colleagues and for being
here it is good to see all of us
together in this chamber today.
I want to first concur what
supervisor dorsey said about
supervisor mandelman.
But for me beyond that his work
and reputation in the public eye
today I concurring and
supporting his presidency also
because the things that he does
when no one is watching.
When how he treat colleagues
respectfully.
When he can agree to disagree
and have the debate be on the
floor in a public ownership
behind our closed door and
having the intimate
conversations he does it
respectful low and intellectual
honesty.
That is all can you ask in a
board PRESIDENT Who can lead us
in unity especially in tough
times to come.
We do have tough times to come.
In terms of the budget deficits
ballooning close to a billion
dollars.
We not only need instant can
lead the legislative branch this
is communicate effectively,
calmly, respectfully with the
executive branch that is someone
we need in this chamber and walk
across this aisle and this
chamber and hallway to room 200
and deliver fruitful, meaningful
successful solutions for san
franciscans for that I want to
express my support for
supervisor mandelman presidency
and lead us.
Thank you.
Supervisor chan.
I will repeat are there other
nominations to be made?
There are no more and we are
closing.
Nominations are closed.
Before discussion can begin on
the nominations, we will take
general public comment.
On this auspicious day and past
the prologue we'll open general
public comment for a minute
today.
for each speaker.
Welcome to our first speaker.
>> [Inaudible] Thank you for
your comments.
Next speaker, please.
Good afternoon.
Mfshs of the board of
supervisors and congratulations
to all of the new electd and
appointed members.
I'm steven with grow sf and I
wanted xrendz a congratulations
to everyone.
Yes,een those we opposed.
We look forward to working with
all ofow our shared objectives
of fixing san francisco's dire
problems.
Including drug addiction,
homelessness and the high cost
of housing.
Congratulations again.
And I look forward to all the
great work you will do the next
4 years.
Thanks.
>> thank you for your comments.
>> before the next speaker I
would ask my staff to check with
the hallway to make sure all
those who would like to comment
are queued up to provide
commentful looks like we have 3
more in line.
Welcome.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
I am mable tang.
Former [Inaudible].
>> welcome.
>>
>> thank you.
I'm thrilled hear the
nominations supervisor dorse and
he supervisor chan.
I wanted to give a shout out to
supervisor mandelman someone I
have worked with since my time.
Of course, he was a baby at that
time we worked together to build
the bridge between china town
and the castro and build
multicultural democracy in san
francisco.
And I look forward to supporting
you everyone on the board and
under PRESIDENT Mandelman's
leadership.
Thank you for your service.
>> thank you, supervisor chang.
I will reset the time are
>> on the same note I'm
commissioner at asian art
museum.
We're frailg facing a lot of
challenges about the art's
program and I hope that we can
work with the board of
supervisors as well as PRESIDENT
Mandelman.
That we are going to still
maintain a balanced budget and
then don't cut our arts program.
>> thank you for your
comments.
>> welcome to our next speaker.
>> good afternoon.
I would like to congratulate all
the newly installed members of
this boulevard I wanted say, I
could not be more excited about
the you'veed a PRESIDENT
Mandelman.
Supervisor mandelman and I have
not agreed on everything and
always respected one another and
I have great respect for him and
think that he can be a bridge
builder
>> thank you.
This MAY be our seconded to last
speaker.
Come up.
>> I'm barbara skin are I. To
congratulate everyone with the
new administration.
We are trying to start a new
organization downtown for san
francisco residents for safe and
clean streets.
And we really welcome a
partnership with the city as the
resident downtown, I have to
tell you it has been awful.
Thank you very much.
>> thank you for sharing your
comments.
Next speaker, welcome.
Good afternoon and
congratulations friends beverly
upton from the domestic violence
consortiumisment to congratulate
and you how much we look forward
to working with you this yack
year.
We are full of home and I know
you, tooshg we look forward to
partnering with you and saving
lives.
Thank you.
>> thank you for sharing your
comments.
Next speaker, please.
Welcome.
>> thank you.
I want to say congratulations
supervisor, thank you for being
our d8 supervisor.
You have been incredible.
We know you bring a 10th when
you do to the district as the
bulled lead this body to great
heights and we got great help
and confidence in you.
Thank you.
>> thank you for sharing your
comments.
>> welcome.
On gloria barry d10.
It is in the exciting times for
me.
San francisco just made the news
number one city in black men
over doses in the nation.
I wish and stress to everyone to
not forget the black community.
If you look at all disparities
where the black community fits
in.
It is disgusting you guys have a
lot of work to do.
we should be in the state of
emergency.
In housing, education, food, in
the fillmore district.
Safe way 50% off sale where are
people go going to get their
food and trader joes is not an
option for the black, asian
community.
Thank you.
Thank you gloria barry for your
comments.
Any other speakers withhold like
to address the board.
My staff are telling me there
are no more speakers with that,
we'll close public comment.
Public comment is closed.
>> now we'll move to the
discussion and election for
PRESIDENT Of the board.
>> to pick up where we left
off.
We will proceed to the
discussion on the nominations
and to the election for board
PRESIDENT.
Before I open discussion I will
share the principles for the
election.
No names.
.
Once I declare discussion open
you miplace your name and
discussion can beginch
discussions are open.
There are no names on the roster
at this point.
>> then, we'll move through to
the principles of the election.
Occurs in alphabetical orders no
extensions or pass vote by
stating preference from among
the nominee.
When called upon.
First nominee to receive the
majority will be the board
PRESIDENT.
Member with the least number
does in the need to with draw.
i can skip this part since there
isn't any.
If nominations, I can skip over
that there is no need to go
further on the principles we
have a name in nominations we'll
begin the election.
There is one name in nominations
that is supervisor dorsey
nominated supervisor mandelman
when your name sell called,
indicate your preference of the
nominee.
I will begin with supervisor
chan.
>> mandelman.
Joof supervisor chen.
>> supervisor dorsey.
>> mandelman.
>> entires engardio.
>> supervisor fielder.
>> mandelman.
>> supervisor mahmood.
>> supervisor mandelman.
>> mandelman for mandelman.
Supervisor melgar.
>> mandelman.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> mandelman.
Supervisor walton.
>> mandelman [Laughter]
Congratulations, supervisor
rafael mandelman.
[Applause] Upon MR. PRESIDENT.
MR. PRESIDENT at this time you
are welcome to invite two
members of the board to escourt
you to the dias.
I would like to call for a
recess to allow you the
opportunity to go to the dias
not until after you assume the
dias and our team will work on
the system to change the names.
Please,
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Thank you colleagueos behalf of
weepy people every where.
I would like to ask that my
colleagues supervisor dorsey and
supervisor chan escourt me to
the dias.
[Applause] All right.
We are back.
Colleagues, should all have
their own -- don't have
computers this week.
All right.
We'll begin with the ramaytush
ohlone land acknowledge am.
The san francisco board of
supervisors acknowledges we are
on the unseed home lands of the
ramaytush ohlone who are the
original inhabitants of the san
francisco peninsula.
As indigenous stewards of the
land the recommend ram never
ceded, lost our forgotten
responsibilities as care take
and ares all in their
traditional territory.
As guests, we recognize we
benefit from living and wing on
their traditional home land.
Wish to pay respects
acknowledging then sesterce and
relatives of the ramaytush
ohlone community and confirming
rights as first peoples.
>> and now00 oo I would like to
start with a moment of silence
for the 39th PRESIDENT Of the
united states PRESIDENT Jimmy
carter.
[Moment of silence] Thank you.
Again I want to thank my
colleagues.
And I will have remarks later
but I wanted say it is a
tremendous honor to serve the
resident in my district, this
board, beautiful city as a
whole.
And so I'm look forward to it.
thank you.
>> we had a lot of federal,
state, local elected officials
today.
I wanted to acknowledge folks
here or were here in the chamber
senator wiener.
Hene.
I think our city add
administrator chu, there she is.
Our city attorney david chu.
Our former city attorney and
general manager of the puc
dennis herrera.
Joaquin torres.
Brook jenkins.
Public defend are.
Sheriff and I think cisneros was
here and greg wagner and lots of
excellent, excellent department
heads.
So I want to thank them and
their staffs for being here.
And watch that, MADAM Clerk call
your next item or do I just go?
MR. PRESIDENT.
Introduction of the mayor item
5.
>> great.
>> earlier today I know many of
us were out in the plaza and
heard your remarks and
congratulations MR. Mayor and
you have come by to share words
with us and we are grateful,
welcome MR. Mayor.
>> thank you, PRESIDENT.
>> is this on?
I was told there is a lot of
seat nothing this room so I'm
standing because it it is a new
day in san francisco.
I want to commend every single
supervisor here today.
We have 5 new ones.
And we have 6 that have
tremendous experience.
That are we are going to lean on
in the coming days, weeks and
months.
president.
Bestowod you a unanimous vote.
I -- don't know when that left
happened?
But what I will tell you is
that -- I see a bright future
for our city because the 11 of
you put aside your differences
for the betterment of our city.
Every one of us got elected
those that were elect in the
NOVEMBER or relected because the
city and county and the
residents of this great city
want results.
And by voting the new PRESIDENT
110 you heard their call.
We are not going to agree on
everything.
We then and there.
That is okay and we can do that
with respect and dignity and I
want to commit to you.
As your mayor working along side
the board PRESIDENT That we are
going to have honest, open
transparent conversation at all
times I promise you that even if
we don't agree its okay.
Got work to do.
And I have to tell you, I am so
optimistic and hope.
Because I know san francisco's
best days are ahead of it.
And -- you know I gave a
sprooech speech out there I did
not write anything for this.
I was not sure if woad go this
quickly.
But what you allowed us to do is
head to china town and have fun
at 5:30!
We will have more fun and can
celebrate the upon 11
supervisors and our new board
PRESIDENT.
Rafael mandelman and I am just
honored.
I look forward to working along
side you.
in partnership and with the 10
of you also in partnership.
New day in san francisco.
And I welcome it.
Thank you.
[Applause]
>> thank you.
MR. Mayor and congratulations
and I do think that this board
is going to do great things with
you and your team and we're look
forward to working with you.
Enjoy the day, sir.
Get out.
All right.
MADAM Clerk call our next item
>> number 6 is to introduce
members who stood for election.
I want to congratulate those of
who you won elections for the
first time and those of you who
are coming back to join us
again.
And I believe this I now get to
introduce each of the new
elected or appointed board
members one by one and each will
have the opportunity to make
brief remarks and introduce
family members and ability to
get to china town for fun depend
whether they are 2 hour or 20
minutes or 2 minutes we will
start with district 1 supervisor
connie chan.
Thank you.
PRESIDENT Mandelman.
I want to thank d1 voters for
confidence in me and their
support so I can continue to
serve them for another 4 years.
My late mother taught me that
serving our community is not
just about be in elected office.
There is no job to big or small.
I know that it is a special
honor to serve san francisco as
an elected leader.
I share this with my team at the
d1 office.
francis shale and robyn burke.
And angelina and our newest
calvinien I'm grafively for work
and dedscasion.
And the most vulnerable and we
continue to do it in city hall
thanks to our brilliant team
esther marx, patti and julie and
kelly grove.
Those who have been part of our
work for the past 4 years we
have faith many challenges.
From take office during a global
pandemic through a tough
recovery for our small
businesses.
Seniors and working people.
We have to fight hard for
resources and support for
vulnerable community.
We make tremendous progress and
surpass phi mile stones the
richmond is the coolest
neighborhoods in the world.
Our team knows that more needs
to be done special we are ready
to get on work.
I will not be able to do this
work if not for my family who I
have never thanked publicly.
And for all the compromises that
we have to make in our daily
lives so that I can be there for
everyone else.
And for all the school events
and soccer games.
Sorry about this.
I want to thank our friends.
Our family, kelly, craig and
code 3 to help getting din are
ready when I can not.
Pick up otto from school or
being our friend.
Being part of our family and
making sure we have a safe space
to enjoy each other's company
with all the thanks I say that
for the most part I understand
the personal sacrifice every
public servant and city worker
must make to make sure our city
governments delivered know
celebrity service.
Thank you, thank you.
I'm thankful to be serving our
city with all of you.
2025 also official low marks the
20th year since the day the
first day I step in city hall to
work for the people of san
francisco.
I know I don't look it, but it
it is true.
I have served under and worked
with 4 mayors and now I'm on to
my fifth.
Along the way I learned a lot.
Learned from ment owor and
friend aaron peskin money,
cannot buy you love and brains.
With just love and brains will
do a lot of great things.
That does not mean tell be easy
and has not been easy.
I learned from speaker nancy
pelosi supported our work in d 1
that it is not easy to keep
serving when integrity in order
to do that well we must know our
why's.
Knowing why we have direction
this remind are has kept me
going on tough days.
For me and clothes for some of
you, the past 20 years, there
have been and I know there will
continue to be tough days ahead.
So I ask myself and probably
you, too, why we continue to do
this work when it gets so tough.
And on those days I reminds
myself they know.
We -- know why.
We love san francisco.
We love san francisco because
this city has been a sanctuary
for all of us.
If you love the city, really
love it, I have faith that it
will always love us back.
this is why today I can say I
know what it takes to make san
francisco the city that knows
how.
It takes a village.
San franciscans who love san
francisco.
We will tackle the 1 billion
dollars budget deficit.
Ensure clean and safe street in
all our neighborhoods.
Will protect our immigrant and
working families and help our
lbgtq+ communities thrive.
And most important low, we do
this together.
I'm grateful that I'm part of
this village as d1 supervisor.
It is a privilege to serve you
and I look forward for 4 more
years.
Thank you.
[Applause]
>> thank you.
Supervisor chan.
>> d2 supervisor steven
sherrill.
>> well, supervisor chan, I
think no one could have said it
better we love san francisco.
And to everyone in the room
thank you for being here you
love san francisco, too.
That sentiment is all we like,
thank you for that.
PRESIDENT Mandelman, thank you.
I am honored stand here today
ready to serve the people of d2
and of san francisco.
I'm so grateful for the
community leaders who supported
mow in this role.
I want to thank lin settleal.
Suzanne swig, bob fisher, jason
pellegrini and kat anderson.
And my family without whole I'm
nothing.
I want to thank my mother kitty
sherbil.
Mother in law.
my father steven sheryl and I
will my wife.
Sarah.
I am excited work with this
phenomenonal bench of colleagues
lead by a great PRESIDENT Rafael
mandelman.
Together, we have great
challenges bawl butteen more
opportunity.
I'm excited work together on
this board every day to build a
better tomorrow for all san
franciscans.
I want to congratulate mayor
lurie he will be an exceptional
partner in all the work to come.
As a father, with young children
in the city, I'm struck by a
tale of two san franciscos.
One where possibility and beauty
are around every corner.
Another where raising a family
on safe and clean streets can
feel daunting.
Now, we stand on a strong
foundation built will a
foundation that is stronger but
must continue to build on that
foundation on the work of mayor
breed and the work and legacy of
my prez seszor catherine
stefani.
Together, with my colleagues we
will build a future where people
can be safe on their
neighborhood streets and
starting a family in san
francisco feasible, affordable
and exciting.
Where small businesses can
succeed.
My first action to call a
hearing on first year free a
program that waves fee and
stream lines permitting for new
small businesses san france what
a flourishing xhshl corridor it
is imperative we ensure programs
like this continue their crucial
work without unnecessary
obstacles.
I'm committed to making san
francisco a city of yes.
Progress and innovation can
thrive and families and
businesses will start, stay and
grow.
At this time d two constituents
I serve I promise to you be on
the graund everground listening
to your needs and carrying out
your priorities.
With my team and I'm luck tow be
surrounded by wonderful people.
Along with my team nile office
will be open to you rain or
shine to tirelessly represent
you and improve our community.
There is no shartage of work to
be done and I cannot wait to get
started, thank you.
[Applause]
>> congratulations, supervisor
sherrill.
There is our d throw supervisor
danny sauter
>> thank you board PRESIDENT
Mandelman.
First my colleagues, I look
forward to working with you in
the important work ahead.
There will be tense moments in
the chambers I know that.
I implore us to point our work
to those outside of city hall.
I'm honored stand here as your
new d3 supervisor representing
incredible neighborhoods and
incredible communities.
This is a privilege I will not
forget what and work every day
to be worthy of this office.
Today I feel luck tow be
surrounded by all those who have
gotten me here and those who
will push me further.
Recognize my team behind me.
Bell, andrews and amy lee.
I feel luck tow have them on my
team and I know san francisco
will feel that way as well.
In the front row, some of my
most family.
Mother, father and brother mark.
Wife chelsea.
Words cannot express how
grateful I feel to have been
raised in such a supportive,
loving setting.
I grew up seeing how they
dedicated their lives to service
my mother a teacher father a
labor lawyer and I will try to
follow in that model and in your
foot steps.
To my wife, chelsea my partner
in friendship and running for
office, and the matter of a few
months doing our best to figure
out a new world as we welcome a
girl in the world.
Chelsea, I love you.
I want to thank the good people
of d throw.
Those who I met through the
years the thousands on door
steps outside corner stores,
neighborhood clean up and it is
farmer's market all took the
time to share with me their
dreams and hopes for san
francisco.
I commit to take these forward
and doing my best to live up to
the ideals of the city.
D throw in san francisco are
ready for results.
They deserve result and that's
what my office will focus on.
The things that make life better
and bright and lower knob hill
create new open space.
Homelessness service are
successful and effective and
china town protect sro tenant
support, small businesses and
zero tolerance for attack on
asian elders.
North beach and russian hill
fill store fronts and ensure
streets are clean and w to keep
neighborhood schools open.
Along the coast, will make sure
this residents tourists and
offices all thrive along side
one another.
District 3 success to san
francisco success we are the
face san francisco.
To visitor in union square and
the war.
Economic engine from hard
working staff and companies
downtown.
Yet we than the parts of san
francisco.
The parts of d throw are ready
for reimagination so we will
pursue plans to add housing,
activity and vibrancy to
neighborhoodses.
The work ahead is serious and it
is sober I know we can do it I
know we must do it san francisco
is too important.
We must be the beacon we know we
can be refuge for those pursues
freedom, opportunity a community
seeking a better life and raise
families and live their san fran
dreams.
San francisco has always shown
what resilience and reinvention
electric like now up to this
generation, this body and
community to ensure weave can
shine brighter, tell our stories
of san francisco with our heads
held high.
Colleagues we have a lot of work
to do so many countingous.
Let's be in and get to work.
Thank you.
[Applause] Congratulations
supervisor sauter.
Next up we have from d5
supervisor mahmood.
>> thank you PRESIDENT And
thank you to supporters, friends
family here.
I want to acknowledge honey
mahogany the leader of the
transgender district and
founder.
She was my inspiration to run
for example supervisor years
ago.
Thank you for being here.
I want to thank my campaign
staff and jessica and will.
Volunteers joes and he
organizers ethan and cameron in
the back.
Without them we would not have
pulled off the biggest upset in
san francisco history.
But most of all I want to thank
my parents first because I want
to thank them for being here but
because I'm the first south
asian to be elected to the board
of supervisors I'm not the first
south asian kid who's parents
think I should have gone to
medical school.
But truly, the reign reason I'm
here to serve d5 is because of
them.
My parents moved here over 40
years ago.
To the city and the bay area
that afforded them a path to
upward mobility.
To establish careers here and
break in the middle class and
raise a family in this country.
And in achieving that dream they
instilled the importance of 3
virtues.
Humanity.
Justice and fairness.
I did take john rols classes in
college.
Humanity and generosity and good
well for neighbor system a
principle we should live.
Justice one person in our
community is hurt the entire
community is hurt.
and fairness, duty to ensure
that every member has a chance
to live a full and dignified
life.
Those are pring principles that
will guide me in d 5 to ensure
our city and the district
returns to the beacon of hope it
once was.
We must ensure our government is
humane, just and fair.
D5 is a unique community.
Beautiful and diverse and more
than anything it is resilient.
The district and people inspire
me to do this work from the
tenderloin to japantown to the
haight this is a community that
does not back down when things
get hard we fight harder when we
have challenges we don't wait we
act.
We bring creativity and
innovation and community
together to solve our toughest
challenges because the residents
of d5 have never begin up hope
on a better future.
Left year I heard loud and clear
to ensure we have mutt humane
and fair d 5 ensure we build
more housing for all san
franciscans are housed.
Safe and clean streets all
families, seniors and children
can walk and enjoy our streets
and our government is working
for the people so our small
businesses generational san
franciscans imnot graves and
refugees have a chance of a full
life tochlt work sthrd is my
pledge I will fight for d5 as
hard as this district fought for
itself I will upon lin to
residents and put the good of
the community first am I will
work beyond lines with anyone.
Upon my new colleagues I look
forward to work with and the old
ones this job is about people
over politics now is the time to
focus practice and delivering
results and crediting the better
tomorrow we all hoped and
dreamed for.
I will daily be a special time
for me and district and all of
us and humble exclude honored to
serve.
Thank you.
[Applause]
>> congratulations temperature
has been awhile I will say upon
since john rols has been cited
in this chamber there is a
handful of polysciers here and
home watching.
Representing d 7 supervisor
melgar.
>> thank you.
PRESIDENT, my family came to san
francisco during the 80s.
From el salvador during the
civil war when I was a child.
This city gave us refuge and
opportunity to thrive.
I want to thank my mother.
Who is here.
We did not grow pickup with her.
There was always a hole if my
heart she went under ground
during the war when I was a kid.
So I want to thank her being
here.
We -- had a long road and san
francisco is the place always
the place where families like
mine can come.
Can come and thrive.
And find freedom whether the
freedom to love who you want top
love.
Or to be who you want to be in
your authentic self to getting
an education.
To be accepted.
And I am so grateful to this
place.
I know we all are for being that
Thank you I am first woman to be
elected supervisor for d 7 and
first latina elected without an
appointment.
And I am glad that now I have
been after reelection another
latina on the board with 4 women
of color in this board that is
more diverse than the last and I
know that we will thrive
together.
And able to represent our
communities as we forge ahead.
I want to thank the rest my
family.
My step father who is here from
spain.
My husband shawn who is one of
the best environmental lawyers
in the country and still manages
to ask me how my day was when I
get home and interested in the
inner workings of what happen in
this building.
My daughters.
Who will all went to school in
district 7 one suspect still in
public schools and keep fight to
make sure that is better.
And I know the rest my family
and sister was here and had to
leave.
I want to thank my staff sorry
you all the best staff in city
hall.
Mike fera, emma here.
Jennifer and jen low for being
the fierce, wonderful, smart
amazing people that serve d7
every day.
Overnight next 4 years I
recommit to work tireless low to
make our neighborhoodses safer,
to build more affordable
housing.
To fight for our city's most
vulnerable populations.
Together, we will ensure that
workers have fair wages.
good working conscience seniors
can live with dignity and he in
safety.
Children can access quality
public sxejz families can
continue to thrive in our city.
The past 4 years were difficult
in this city we are not out of
the woods.
Erosion of down town vibrancy of
our tax bachls a drug crisis
that is killing so many of our
residents and destroying
families.
Struggling schools with kids who
need our support.
And still racial disparities a
housing crisis.
That we must tackle.
To make sure that san francisco
can thrive.
I'm proud of behalf this left
board accomplished in the past 4
years spill than working
together collaborative low with
our new mayor and my new
colleague on the board we can
continue to tackle the issues
and solve themful I commit to
doing so with maintaining
civility and respect for all of
you across differences.
With the goal of achieving
practical result.
I pledge to condition working
for a better west side with my
other west side colleagues.
We'll tackle the issues facing
our communities that are unique
to the west side.
From enhancing public safety and
making housing more affordable.
And more abundant to improving
and improving environmental
sustain ability.
Challengeers significant I'm
confident that we can tackle
them together and I pledge to
continue to work hard to
prioritize housing affordable
housing.
A fair and accessible transit
system that works for all of us.
Universal childcare a promise we
have been making for years and
service to kits they are our
prurt.
Reduce or carbon footprint and
address the impact we are having
on climate.
We owe it to the next
generation.
We will continue to work
together.
With our public safety
departments and make sure that
they are fully staffed that
their staffing the diversity of
race, jendz and cultures in san
francisco.
And they are properly equipped.
I remain committed to the rep
centation of women.
In leadership at all levels of
our city includeing board.
And that of top defends all
human rights of our people.
Women.
Lbgtq+ minorities against the
possible attacks from this
federal administration.
Lastly, thank you all for your
unwaivering support and trust
I'm excited serve our city and
beyond grateful to have you all
in the journey tow continue the
create a city all children can
dream big where families
fleurish and every individual
has the opportunity to succeed.
Thank you.
[Applause].
>> congratulations.
Supervisor melgar and from d 9,
supervisor jackie fielder.
[Applause] I introduce myself in
spanish and -- my grand mother's
language to my father's side and
my mom and grand ma's language
on my mom's side my mom is right
in front of me.
Recording the entire meeting
double for sfgovtv.
Honor of representing d9 and we
have been busy since election
day me and my amazing team to
check in with our district and
get a pulse for what is the
latest.
So I'm speak from this heart
today I have nothing prepared.
Am but I want to thank my mom,
who raised me for most of my
life as a single mom.
United secretary.
Who takes the bus every wrchlt
and has inspired me to defend
public transportation.
I want to thank my dad who will
be at my inauguration next week.
A tremendous rock in my life.
I want to thank my sister here.
Who is a freshman at berkeley
and has been ply rock for many
years.
Despite our age difference.
But my grandparents and my
family come from very humble
beginnings.
My grandparentos my dad side
survived boarding schools and
systemic asimulation.
Going even further back we
survived the genocide of the
country.
And so -- my presence here is a
miracle.
And that is why I have the
[Inaudible] To seize every
opportunity I had.
And so00 this is not just for
myself but my family.
For our entire lineage.
And both directions lacoata and
mexico.
And so I wanted take a moment to
honor their memory and my family
and all of our struggles to be
in the moment with me.
I want to thank my chosen family
who have been there from I have
my best friends from high
school.
Chris.
I have marcos and many loved
ones in the audience who is here
today.
Who comprise my chosen family in
san francisco.
And who have been my home for a
long time.
I incredibly thankful to the d 9
voter who is -- gave us the
stung margins of 60%.
And that is due in no small part
to our grass-roots volunteers.
Tremendous campaign staff.
Especially sascha behind me who
have been able to join me now.
I'm honored to serve the
neighborhoods of mission, bernal
and he will portola.
I will be a supervisor for
everyone.
I want to thank also anna
herrera.
Jennifer for continuing to serve
in the district 9 office.
And make this an increditedicly
smooth transition.
Thank a number of supervisors
for welcome me and giving me
helpful advice and serving as
mentors first off supervisor
preston.
My former colleague on the lafco
commission.
And cone chan.
Supervisor ronen and tammy
amiano in d 9 we have many
challenges.
In d9 on whiches, we are
focussed on public safety.
On clean streets.
Making sure our city remains a
sanctuary city for all.
Making sure our lbgtq+ community
and our transcommunity will not
be left behind in this
administration.
we have a national crisis and
someone who has loved once fact
affected with addiction I'm
looking forward to working to
make sure that treatment and
infrastructure and real
treatment on demand becomes
reality and not just a talking
point.
As a renter, I am also very much
proud to continue to serve
tenants across the city who
continue to struggle and battle
with eviction crisis that has
not been fully resolved since
the pandemic.
We cannot and will not leave
behind the most vulnerable in
the time of austerity.
We will not leave workers.
We will not leave behind our
undocumentedim grant neighbors.
Not leave the 1700 unhoused
students in this city.
In the same city we have dozens
of billionaires.
We will not leave behind our
planet.
Thank you supervisor melgar for
mentioning our relationship and
our responsibility to take care
of our one home and there is a
lot of talk today about making
sure that san francisco remains
a city for all.
And as language as we are here
and as long as we have the
amazing cultural organizing00
ago resource in d 9, we'll be
here to make sure that this city
it is a city for all.
Thank you.
[Applause] Congratulations
supervisor fielder.
Last but never least.
Supervisor chen.
>> thanks.
Thank you, PRESIDENT Mandelman.
Thank you everyone for being
here today.
first like everyone I would like
to say appreciation to my family
of they left.
They left the room.
Because with a young girl it is
hard for her to sit here you
know with a bunch of [Inaudible]
I want to also thank them that
they were here and I without my
family support I would not be
here today.
To that, I want to extend my
thank you to my labor alli who
is invested a lot in the
campaign.
I can be here.
And I want to express my
gratitude to my supporters.
To my community leaders and to
everyone in d11 that who placed
their trust in me to bring the
victory home and d 11 will not
be unheard.
D11 will be visible under my
leadership.
To that I ulc want to say that
it is a tremendous honor to
become a supervisor but come
with responsibility.
Every day that I hold my heart.
To embrace it every day.
It is important that district 11
my campaign, came with a theme
of unity.
Unity is a string that district
11 will continue to embrailles.
And district 11 is rich with
people that will truly embody
the spirits of our city.
Because we do have working
families.
That tackling and fighting to
stay in san francisco every day.
To the teachers and the
community leaders and the
artists and young leaders who
bring vibrancy throughout san
francisco every day and also to
our local moms and pops
restaurant owners, shopkeepers
who invest in our neighborhood
economy.
They have we have to support
them.
They always a vibrant and
essential part of our community.
D 11 come together to show
unity.
Because we bring people cross
generation and background
together to tackle the
challenges that is not just in d
11 it is the entire city.
That I don'tment to name it
again we have heard enough
today.
And I will continue to commit to
work hard to ensure that our
working families, children and
youth, seniors and our small
business ordinance in district
11 and the city to make sure we
can continue top have a voice to
make sure that san francisco can
continue to belong to a place
where we want to stay and we can
stay here.
And will I'm also excited roll
up my sleeve to continue to make
sure I lin to our constate wents
and listen to the voices of our
community with humble
transparency and to mitt to work
collaborative low to make sure
we continue top bring the unity
the partnership to solve the
challenge in d11 and the city.
I have faith that today is also
a demonstration of unity.
We will continue to work
together and I also look forward
to continue to work with my new
colleagues on the board and also
to look forward to make sure I'm
not only working with our
supervisors but with the amazing
staff and with that I want to
make sure I thank my staff team.
Jack and he charl and he upon
lynn another staff out sickt
happen this is is also means
that it is really important that
we work together to support each
other in in room.
And for that I'm really looking
forward to continue to work
together and cultivate and
foster in tan san francisco we
feel proud of, thank you.
[Applause].
Congratulations, supervisor
chen.
I want to offer the opportunity
to continuing members to offer
comments if they want to they
don't have to.
Supervisor engardio.
>> thank you.
I want to say it is really
exciting to be serving in this
moment with this new board in
this new day in san francisco.
With the new board members just
two years ago I was the newest
board member if I give advice it
is like we near this unique 11
person boat.
And we are here together we need
to row together there will be
choppy access some days feel I
want to three that person out of
the boat that will not help us
we need to row together and I
think one way to do that is get
to know your fellow supervisors.
Don't make assumptions you never
know who you will connect with I
tried to work with everyone on
the previous board and there
were surprises where we clickd
and worked together and I
encourage getting to know people
go in offices and talk.
Meet for coffee.
Get to know people as human
beings and colleagues.
And sometimes in politics we are
presented as characters we are
real get to know each other to
row together.
a baptist advice is there will
be times there is very tough
decisions we have to make and we
have to think of are we making a
principled stand or what are we
going to do?
Pressure.
What I try to do is think of an
anchor or a role model.
For example will I know we are
honoring and morning former
PRESIDENT Carter today.
But for a number of years hi a
plaque above my desk that said
what would jimmy carter do?
I try to when faced with a
difficult decision mao how I do
face it with humanity.
Humility, kindness and
thoughtful knows.
I encourage to you think of your
touch stones.
And finally, we have a lot of
challenges we need to address
here in san francisco.
And as we work and fix the
problems, we have to always
remember that no matter what
challenges we are face thering
is joy in the city.
We need to celebrate the joy
naexists and work to create more
joy that is the ultimate goal we
are here to create.
And honored be here to do that
work with you.
Thank you.
[Applause].
Supervisor walton
>> thank you.
PRESIDENT Mandelman, I want to
say this public low.
Congratulations to all of my new
colleagues both electd and
appointed.
And I want to congratulate you,
PRESIDENT Mandelman for
duplicating a feat I did a
couple years ago and getting one
vote passes for the presidency.
But I do want to congratulate
you -- and look forward to
working closely with the new
board and with the PRESIDENT.
And just reminds you we will not
agree on everything but most
certainly we are here to get
this work done.
So, congratulations everyone and
looking forward to the work
ahead.
>> thank you.
Supervisor walton.
>> [Applause] MADAM Clerk call
our next item
>> item 7.
This item provides remarks by
the honorable PRESIDENT Of the
san francisco board of
supervisors.
>> so a funny thing happens
will when you think you might
possible low get elected
PRESIDENT Of the board of
supervisors that about upon 1:35
or 1:40 you think, man I gotta
say something today.
And I have been first of all I
want to thank my colleagues.
For policing your trust in me
with this job.
I will do my best not to let any
of you down in this trust.
I want it thank the d8 voter who
is 6 and a half years ago
decided to send mow in this
building.
And their having done that now
makes me by sick months the most
senior person on this board.
Which gives me the office in the
corner which was the office of
the first gay board PRESIDENT
Harry britt.
And when I was a high school
student, and a bit of a homo
phobe in the late 80s and had an
internship for doris award near
this building, I remember
walking by that office and being
simultaneous low intrigued and
concerned what might happen
fispent too much time near that
office.
Now I get to spend two years
there.
Thank you harry britt and thank
you to all of the folks who
worked so hard to allow the
queer folks to create space and
the other folks who might not
have been here to be in the
chamber and this building.
>> I'm the old guy.
And I do have MAY be this is
advice for colleagues but a
thought about the moment that we
are in.
I have learned in this time, in
the years that the gentleman of
the city and county of san
francisco is a big complicated
thing.
There are people who have work
in the this government for
decades.
Trying to figure out how to make
it do better things for the
people of the city of san
francisco.
There are people who have been
elected by voters and tried to
serve in the building and tried
to make that positive change and
it it is often hard for the
folks me include.
To figure out exactly which
levers need to be moved.
Which gears need to be greased.
Which buttons we push.
To deliver for our people.
There are knots every where.
And for good or ill we are a
city of abundant checks and
balances.
And so, part of that choice
things we have done to ourselves
some of it bibbing in the
structure was our gentleman
around for decades to get
anything done in our system
requires good faith, trust and a
word that our new mayor quoting
my predecessor mentioned.
Hope.
In the past 6 years those
@electronicallies have been in
short supply.
Today, and is a new day.
We have a new mayor.
We have a new board of
supervisors with 5 new members.
And I know from talking to each
and every one of you, that each
and every one of you wanted this
mayor to succeed and I know from
talking to our new mayor that he
wants to and believes he can
work with each and everyone of
us.
And that is just an
extraordinary opportunity which
we need because we are entering
a period of extraordinary
challenge.
As amongst ourselves and
supervisor walton noted, we have
andy will surely disagree on
this or that policy or priority.
And that's our job.
There is time and space for
that.
Some of us, are going to I think
this is correct.
Demand that the city live up to
its legacy a lead in the fight
for social justice.
And some of us and I thank you
is correct, are going to demand
that we prioritize the fortunate
and effective delivery of public
service.
And those priorities are shared
by all of us.
Are not always or necessary low
in conflict.
There can be no social justice
without effective government and
government cannot exceed without
social justice.
Our task is to figure out how to
pursue both
>> the measure and time line and
how we get there.
I have so much hope -- that this
is a set of folks here and there
and out in san francisco, who
are going to be committed to
that and this we are going to be
this great blue city on the
pacific coast that will show
people how to get things done.
We are lucky folks mentioned our
staff.
I'm grateful to mine.
To calvin ho and henry andan.
I'm so sorry I'm doing this to
you.
For all of the other staff we
are so grateful, I'm so excited
this is such an amazing crew of
people with so many different
experiences in this building
outside of this building.
I beg your patience.
We beg your patience we will
figure this out and do our
fwoeft get this -- guide this
board, of course, it will be
angela and her people who tell
us what to do.
And angela thank you, angela!
Thank you to your team!
[Applause] And brad and david
will keep from us violating the
law and thank you!
[Applause] And I think almost no
, I those are I think my remarks
I'm looking forward to this,
thank you all.
MADAM Clerk do we have further
business before us today?
MR. PRESIDENT that concludes our
business for today.
My goodness, we are adjourned.